Vicente S. Acosta papers, 1947-1983
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Papers of Vicente S. Acosta, 1947-1983
SWF 006
Acosta, Vicente S., 1918-1983
5 linear feet
The Papers of Vicente S. Acosta contains professional correspondence, manuscripts and essays, research materials, and audio tapes documenting Acosta's interests in the Spanish language, folk songs and folklore and Southwestern United States and Mexican culture.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Vicente S. Acosta was born in 1918. He taught Spanish and served as chair of the Spanish department at Santa Rita High School in Tucson, Arizona. He developed an interest in numerous elements of Southwestern folklore, such as folksongs, herbal remedies, and the way the people of the region used the Spanish language in their everyday speech and communication. Acosta received a B.A. degree from the University of Arizona. He served as a member of the University's Folklore Committee in the 1940s and 1950s, and earned an M.A. degree from the University in 1951. Acosta continued collecting folklore materials and conducting research throughout his career as a teacher, focusing most of his collecting activities and investigations on folksongs and corridos. Acosta died in 1983.
Organization
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Correspondence, 1963-1978
II. Publications and Essays, 1950-1983
III. Research and Field Notes, 1947-circa.1983
IV. Audio Materials, 1964-1967
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1947-1983, of Tucson, Arizona, Spanish teacher and folklorist, Vicente Sanchez Acosta (1918-1983). Contains professional correspondence, manuscripts and essays, research materials, and audio tapes documenting Acosta's interests in the Spanish language, folk songs and folklore and Southwestern United States and Mexican culture.
The collection includes professional correspondence between Acosta and his colleagues and informants on topics related to his interests in Spanish-language songs and song forms, Spanish personal names and nicknames, and herbal remedies. Also included are copies of Acosta's essays and presentations, as well as several drafts of his M.A. thesis, one of which includes manuscript corrections. The collection also includes audiotapes made by Acosta as he conducted his research. Some tapes include song performances discussed in his master's thesis; others contain recordings of spoken Spanish which he used in his research on the Spanish language and its spoken characteristics.
The final accepted version of Acosta's University of Arizona M.A. thesis is located in the Main and Special Collections libraries, at call number E 9791 1951 1.
Access Terms
Acosta, Vicente Sanchez, 1918-
Teachers -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Archives
Folklorists -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Archives
Folklore -- Mexico
Folklore -- Southwest, New
Herbs -- Folklore
Herbs -- Therapeutic use
Corridos
Folk songs, Spanish -- Southwest, New
Names, Personal -- Arizona -- Tucson
Names, Spanish -- Arizona -- Tucson
Spanish language -- Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.
Spanish language -- Slang
Correspondence
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1963-1978
  Professional correspondence between Acosta and his colleagues and informants on topics related to his interests in Spanish-language songs and song forms, Spanish surnames, and herbal remedies.
  - Correspondence. 1963-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Publications and Essays, 1950-1983
  Published and unpublished papers, essays and talks given by Acosta on Spanish-language songs, ballads and corridos, Spanish slang and word play, and herbal remedies and folklore. Includes Spanish-English glossaries for medical and educational vocabularies, early drafts of his works on Spanish surnames, Ibero-American Roots of Tucson, Arizona and Raices Ibero-Americanas de Tucson, Arizona. Includes two drafts, one with manuscript corrections, and a transcript of the field recordings of his University of Arizona M.A. thesis, Some Surviving Aspects of Spanish Folklore in Arizona. The transcript of tape recordings is dated 1962.
  - Some Surviving Elements of Spanish Folklore in Arizona (M.A. thesis draft with manuscript corrections). 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Some Surviving Elements of Spanish Folklore in Arizona (M.A. thesis draft; no title page; incomplete). 1951? (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Some Surviving Elements of Spanish Folklore in Arizona (transcript of recordings used in M.A. thesis [?]). 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Spanish Ballad in Arizona History. 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hipocorísticos y sobrenombres. 1967? (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Some Remedies Collected from Oral Tradition and Some Remedies Collected Through Herb Stores. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Some Remedies Collected from Oral Tradition and Some Remedies Collected Through Herb Stores [another copy]. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Homenaje al Sr. Guadalupe Armenta. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Homenaje al Sr. Guadalupe Armenta [another copy]. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A Dental Glossary: English-Spanish. 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - A Spanish-English Glossary of Educational Terminology Used in Mexican Schools. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ibero-American roots of Tucson, Arizona. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Raices Ibero-Americanas de Tucson, Arizona. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Origin and meaning of Ibero-American surnames in Tucson, Arizona. 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Untitled essay on corridos. No Date (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Léxico fronterizo de Arizona. No Date (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - El romance español y el corrido mexicano. No Date (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series III: Research and Field Notes, 1947-circa.1983
  Research notes and materials used by Acosta for his study of the Spanish language, Spanish language and slang, and folklore, including herbal remedies.
  - "Vocabulario de la poesia Gauchesca ..." (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Spanish word play. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mexican proverbs; "refranes y dichos mexicanos." (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Algunos horrores de paulabrous spawniolas [sic]." 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Glossaries: baseball, "fraces y palabras parlamentarias," legal. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Herbal remedies. 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Dance directions. 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
  - Bibliographies. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Estudio paremiológico. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous folklore notes. 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Notes for Ibero-American roots of Tucson, Arizona. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Notes for Hipocorísticos y sobrenombres. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Notes for Origin and meaning of Ibero-American surnames in Tucson, Arizona. (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
  - "Spanish folklore collection of Vincente [sic] Acosta, Tucson, Arizona." (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - La Llorona; la sirena. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Oversized illustration for Raices Ibero-Americanas de Tucson, Arizona. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Romances. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Revolution songs," and folksongs from my thesis; Paco Río, etc. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lyrics for corridos, etc., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Survival of Spanish folklore in Arizona; notes and transcripts of corridos., 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Yo no me caso, compadre;" other folksongs. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Spanish-language song books., 1950s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Corridos por el Señor Torres., June 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notecards with notes on the origins of Spanish surnames. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Listing of Vicente Acosta tape reels. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Audio Materials, 1964-1967
  Audio tape recordings of interviews, field recordings, and recordings of Spanish songs used by Acosta in his research on songs and the Spanish language. This series includes Acosta’s tape recordings used in the creation of his University of Arizona M.A. thesis. Two sets of eleven tape reels are labeled as thesis tapes, both with roman numeral designations. For purposes of arrangement, the folders for the second series are identified with the roman numeral found on the tape containers, followed by the letter "B" to designate them as the second series.
  - "The Spanish Ballad in Arizona History: Songs of José Lisorio and El Merino" (Paper submitted to the Arizona Historical Association). (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Entrevista, 22 Jan. 1967: Spanish nicknames; sobrenombres., January 22, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Platica de Sr. José Fierros y Sr. José Felix; cuentos de Don Cocahuate; corridos, etc. for linguistic study., February 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Platica José Fierros, Ruben Camacho (Gardener's)., March 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Entrevista Oct. 1966: remedios Ch. Seros; Platica del remedio del yerba. October 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Short sentences; occlusive "B"; Gardener's talk (U of A). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Peru and Venezuela; Irel Urreiztiera. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Apr. '67, José Fierros; "El tragareces"; Charrai "Cup of coffee.", April 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - El romance y el corrido: conference given to folklore class. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Program on KUAT, Channel 6., January 14, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Thesis I-XI. (Box 3, Folder 11-21)
  - Thesis I-III B. (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
  - Thesis III-IV B. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Thesis IV-V B. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Thesis IV [sic]-VII B. (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
  - Thesis VII-VIII B. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Thesis IX-X B. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Thesis XI B. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Romances; corridos; songs from the "thesis" (in order of their appearance in the book). (Box 5, Folder 4)